<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Amir Chaudhry - 'OCaml'</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/tags/ocaml-atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com"/>
  <subtitle>thoughts, comments &amp; general ramblings</subtitle>
  <updated>2015-01-21T14:42:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/tags/#ocaml</id>
  <author>
    <name>Amir Chaudhry</name>
  </author>
  
    <entry>
  <title>Brewing MISO to serve Nymote</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/brewing-miso-to-serve-nymote"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2015-01-20T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/brewing-miso-to-serve-nymote</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/blog/2013/introducing-nymote/&quot;&gt;mission of Nymote&lt;/a&gt; is to enable the creation of resilient
decentralised systems that incorporate privacy from the ground up, so that
users retain control of their networks and data.  To achieve this, we
reconsider all the old assumptions about how software is created in light of
the problems of the modern, networked environment.  Problems that will become
even more pronounced as more devices and sensors find their way into our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make it simple for anyone to be able to run a piece of the cloud
for their own purposes and the first three applications Nymote targets are
Mail, Contacts and Calendars, but to get there, we first have to create solid
foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Defining the bedrock&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to create applications that work for the user, we first have to
create a robust and reliable software stack that takes care of fundamental
problems for us. In other words, to be able to assemble the applications we
desire, we must first construct the correct building blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We've taken a clean-slate approach so that we can build long-lasting solutions
with all the benefits of hindsight but none of the baggage. As
mentioned in earlier posts, there are three main components of the stack,
which are: &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/software/mirage/&quot;&gt;Mirage&lt;/a&gt; (OS for the Cloud/IoT), &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/software/irmin/&quot;&gt;Irmin&lt;/a&gt; (distributed datastore)
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/software/signpost/&quot;&gt;Signpost&lt;/a&gt; (identity and connectivity) - all built using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt;
programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Using the MISO stack to build Nymote&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you've already noticed, there's a useful acronym for the above tools —
&lt;strong&gt;MISO&lt;/strong&gt;. Each of the projects mentioned is a serious undertaking in its own
right and each is likely to be impactful as a stand-alone concept.  However,
when used together we have the opportunity to create applications and services
with high levels of security, scalability and stability, which are not easy to
achieve using other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, MISO is the &lt;em&gt;toolstack&lt;/em&gt; that we're using to build Nymote —
Nymote is the &lt;em&gt;decentralised system&lt;/em&gt; that works for its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the projects is at a different phase but they have all have made great
strides over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Mirage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirage — a library operating system that constructs unikernels — is the most
mature part of the stack. I previously wrote about the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/blog/2014/announcing-first-mirage-release/&quot;&gt;Mirage 1.0 release&lt;/a&gt; and only six months later we had an
&lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org/blog/announcing-mirage-20-release&quot;&gt;impressive 2.0 release&lt;/a&gt;, with continuing advances throughout the year.
We achieved major milestones such as the ability to deploy unikernels to
ARM-based devices, as well as a clean-slate implementation of the transport
layer security (TLS) protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the development efforts, there have also been many
presentations to audiences, ranging from &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/describing-miso-entrepreneur-first-2014/&quot;&gt;small groups of startups&lt;/a&gt;
all the way to &lt;a href=&quot;http://media.ccc.de/browse/congress/2014/31c3_-_6443_-_en_-_saal_2_-_201412271245_-_trustworthy_secure_modular_operating_system_engineering_-_hannes_-_david_kaloper.html#video&quot;&gt;prestigious keynotes&lt;/a&gt; with 1000+ attendees.  Ever
since we've had ARM support, the talks themselves have been delivered from
unikernels running on Cubieboards and you can see the growing collection of
slides at &lt;a href=&quot;http://decks.openmirage.org&quot;&gt;decks.openmirage.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these activities have led to a tremendous increase in public awareness
of unikernels and the value they can bring to developing robust, modern
software as well as the promise of &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@darrenrush/after-docker-unikernels-and-immutable-infrastructure-93d5a91c849e&quot;&gt;immutable infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;.
As more people look to get involved and contribute to the codebase, we've also
begun curating a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-www/wiki/Pioneer-Projects&quot;&gt;Pioneer Projects&lt;/a&gt;, which are suitable for a
range of skill-levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find much more information on all the activities of 2014 in the
comprehensive &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org/blog/2014-in-review&quot;&gt;Mirage review post&lt;/a&gt;. As it's the most mature
component of the MISO stack, anyone interested in the &lt;em&gt;development of code&lt;/em&gt;
towards Nymote should join the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.xenproject.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/mirageos-devel&quot;&gt;Mirage mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source code&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage&quot;&gt;Mirage org on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Irmin&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irmin — a library to persist and synchronize distributed data structures —
made significant progress last year. It's based on the principles of Git, the
distributed version control system, and allows developers to choose the
appropriate combination of consistency, availability and partition tolerance
for their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early last year Irmin was released as an alpha with the ability to speak
'fluent Git' and by the summer, it was supporting user-defined merge
operations and fast in-memory views.  A couple of summer projects improved the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://gazagnaire.org/pub/FGM15.pdf&quot;&gt;merge strategies&lt;/a&gt; and synchronisation strategies, while an
external project — Xenstore — used Irmin to &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org/blog/introducing-irmin-in-xenstore&quot;&gt;add fault-tolerance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent work has involved a big clean-up in the user-facing API (with nice
&lt;a href=&quot;http://samoht.github.io/irmin/&quot;&gt;developer documentation&lt;/a&gt;) and a cleaner high-level REST API.
Upcoming work includes proper documentation of the REST API, which means Irmin
can more easily be used in non-OCaml projects, and full integration with
Mirage projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irmin is already being used to create
&lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/imaplet-lwt/imaplet-lwt.0.1.3/&quot;&gt;a version controlled IMAP server&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/samoht/dog&quot;&gt;a version controlled distributed log system&lt;/a&gt;. It's no surprise
that the first major release is coming &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/irmin/issues?q=is%3Aopen+is%3Aissue+milestone%3A1.0.0&quot;&gt;very soon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source code&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/irmin&quot;&gt;Irmin on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Signpost&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signpost will be a collection of libraries that aims to provide identity and
connectivity between devices.  Forming efficient connections between
end-points is becoming ever more important as the number of devices we own
increases. These devices need to be able to recognise and reach each-other,
regardless of their location on the network or the obstacles in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very much a nascent project and it involves a lot of work on
underlying libraries to ensure that security aspects are properly considered.
As such, we must take great care in how we implement things and be clear about
any trade-offs we make. Our thoughts are beginning to converge on a design we
think will work and that we would entrust with our own data, but we're
treating this as a case of 'Here Be Dragons'.  This is a critical piece of the
stack and we'll share what we learn as we chart our way towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we're at the design stage of Signpost, we did substantial work
last year to create the libraries we might use for implementation.  A
particularly exciting one is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MagnusS/jitsu&quot;&gt;Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; — which stands for Just In Time
Summoning of Unikernels. This is a DNS server that spawns unikernels in
response to DNS requests and boots them in real-time with no perceptible lag
to the end user.  In other words, it makes much more efficient use of
resources and significantly reduces latency of services for end-users —
services are only run &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; they need to be, in the &lt;em&gt;places&lt;/em&gt; they need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's also been lots of efforts on other libraries that will help us
&lt;em&gt;iterate towards&lt;/em&gt; a complete solution. Initially, we will use pre-existing
implementations but in time we can take what we've learned and create more
robust alternatives. Some of the libraries are listed below (but note the
friendly disclaimers!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source code&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dsheets/ocaml-sodium&quot;&gt;Bindings to libsodium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dsheets/ocaml-dnscurve&quot;&gt;Implementation of DNSCurve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dsheets/ocaml-libmacaroons&quot;&gt;Bindings to libmacaroons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;OCaml&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt; is a mature, powerful and highly pragmatic language.  It's
proven ideal for creating robust systems applications and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/learn/companies.html&quot;&gt;many others&lt;/a&gt; also recognise this.  We're using it to create all the
tools you've read about so far and we're also helping to improve the ecosystem
around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major things we've been involved with is the coordination of the
OCaml Platform, which combines the OCaml compiler with a coherent set of tools
and workflows to be more productive in the language and speed up development
time.  We presented the first major release of these efforts at OCaml 2014 and
you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/meetings/ocaml/2014/ocaml2014_7.pdf&quot;&gt;read the abstract&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jxhtpQ5nJHg&amp;amp;list=UUP9g4dLR7xt6KzCYntNqYcw&quot;&gt;watch the video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's more to come, as we continue to improve the tooling and also support
the community in &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/towards-governance-framework-for-ocamlorg&quot;&gt;other ways&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Early steps towards applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building blocks are important but we also need to push towards working
applications.  There are different approaches we've taken to this, which
include building prototypes, wireframing use-cases and implementing features
with other toolstacks.  Some of this work is also part of a larger
&lt;a href=&quot;http://usercentricnetworking.eu&quot;&gt;EU funded project&lt;/a&gt;* and below are brief summaries of the things we've
done so far. We'll expand on them as we do more over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mail&lt;/strong&gt; - As mentioned above, a prototype IMAP server exists (&lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/imaplet-lwt/imaplet-lwt.0.1.3/&quot;&gt;IMAPlet&lt;/a&gt;)
which uses Irmin to store data. This is already able to connect to a client to
serve mail. The important feature is that it's an IMAP server which is version
controlled in the backend and can expose a REST API from the mailstore quite
easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt; - We first made wireframe mockups of the features we might like
in a contacts app (to follow in later post) and then built a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yansh/contacts-app&quot;&gt;draft implementation&lt;/a&gt;. To get here, code was first written in OCaml
and then put through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocsigen.org/js_of_ocaml/&quot;&gt;js_of_ocaml&lt;/a&gt; compiler. This is valuable as it
takes us closer to a point where we can build networks using our address books
and have the system take care of sharing details in a privacy-conscious manner
and with minimal maintenance. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://yansnotes.blogspot.co.uk/2015/01/work-summary-ocaml-labs.html&quot;&gt;summary post&lt;/a&gt; has more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calendar&lt;/strong&gt; - This use-case was approached in a completely different way as
part of a hackathon last year. A rough but functional prototype was built over
one weekend, with a team formed at the event.  It was centralised but it
tested the idea that a service which integrates intimately with your life (to
the point of being very invasive) can provide disproportionate benefits.  The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://seedcamp.com/seedhack-5-0/&quot;&gt;experience report&lt;/a&gt; describes the weekend and our app — Clarity —
won first place. This was &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; validation that the features are desirable
so we need to work towards a decentralised, privacy-conscious version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Time to get involved!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coming year represents the best time to be working on the MISO stack and
using it to make Nymote a reality.  All source code is publicly available and
the projects are varied enough that there is something for everyone.  Browse
through issues, consider the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-www/wiki/Pioneer-Projects&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; or simply write online and
share with us the things you'd like to see.
This promises to be an exciting year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;* The research leading to these results has received
funding from the European Union's Seventh Framework Programme FP7/2007-2013
under the UCN project, grant agreement no 611001.
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;!-- ========================================================= --&gt;



</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Unikernels for everyone!</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/unikernels-for-everyone"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2015-01-19T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/unikernels-for-everyone</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people have now set up unikernels for blogs, documenting their
experiences for others to follow.  Even more important is that people are
going beyond static sites to build unikernels that provide more complicated
services and solve real-world problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help newcomers get started, there are now even more posts that that use
different tools and target different deployment methods.  Below are summaries
of some of the posts I found interesting and that will make it easier for you
try out different ways of creating and deploying your unikernels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Unikernel blogs with MirageOS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindy picked up where the &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/from-jekyll-to-unikernel-in-fifty-lines/&quot;&gt;first set of instructions&lt;/a&gt;
finished and described her work to get an Octopress blog running on Amazon EC2.
As one of the first people outside the core team to work on this, she had a
lot of interesting experiences — which included getting into the Mirage
networking stack to debug an issue and submit a bugfix!  More recently, she
also wrote a couple of excellent posts on &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; she uses a unikernel for her
blog.  These posts cover the security concerns (and responsibility) of running
networked services on today's Internet and the importance of owning your
content — both ideas are at the heart of the work behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/&quot;&gt;Nymote&lt;/a&gt; and are
well worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindy's posts&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overview&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.somerandomidiot.com/blog/2014/08/18/i-am-unikernel/&quot;&gt;&quot;I Am Unikernel (and So Can You!)&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;First in her Mirage series&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.somerandomidiot.com/blog/2014/03/14/its-a-mirage/&quot;&gt;&quot;It's a Mirage! (or, How to Shave a Yak.)&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.somerandomidiot.com/blog/2014/08/11/attack-surface-area/&quot;&gt;&quot;Attack Surface: Why I Unikernel, Part 1&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.somerandomidiot.com/blog/2014/08/14/my-content-is-mine/&quot;&gt;&quot;My Content Is Mine: Why I Unikernel, Part 2&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ian took a different path to AWS deployment by using Vagrant and Test Kitchen
to to get his static site together and build his unikernel, and then Packer to
create the images for deployment to EC2.  All succinctly explained with code
available on GitHub for others to try out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ian on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iw/mirage-jekyll&quot;&gt;&quot;Mirage with Jekyll on Amazon EC2&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Toby wanted to put together a blog that was a little more complicated than a
traditional static site, with specific features like subdomains based on tags
and the ability to set future dates for posts. He also pulled in some other
libraries so he can use Mustache for sever-side rendering, where his blog
posts and metadata are stored as JSON and rendered on request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toby on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.is-awesome.net/2014/11/building-a-blog-with-mirage-os&quot;&gt;&quot;Building a Blog with MirageOS&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Chris saw others working to get unikernel blogs on EC2 and decide he'd try
getting his up and running on Linode instead.  He is the first person to
deploy his unikernel to Linode and he provided a great walkthough with helpful
screenshots, as well as brief notes about the handful of differences compared
with EC2.  Chris also wrote about the issue he had with clean urls (i.e
serving &lt;code&gt;/about/index.html&lt;/code&gt; when a user visits &lt;code&gt;/about/&lt;/code&gt;) — he describes the
things he tried out until he was finally able to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chris' posts&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Setting up a unikernel&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://christopherbothwell.com/ocaml/mirage/2014/12/03/about-not-found.html&quot;&gt;&quot;About Not Found&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deploying to Linode&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://christopherbothwell.com/ocaml/mirage/linode/2014/12/08/hello-linode.html&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello Linode&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Phil focused on getting unikernels running on a cubieboards, which are ARM
based development boards — similar to the Raspberry Pi. He starts by taking
Mirage's pre-built &lt;a href=&quot;http://blobs.openmirage.org&quot;&gt;Cubieboard images&lt;/a&gt; — which makes it easy to
get Xen and an OCaml environment set up on the board — and getting this
installed on the Cubieboard.  He also noted the issues he came across along
with the simple tweaks he made to fix them and finally serves a Mirage hello
world page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phil on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://philtomson.github.io/blog/2014/09/10/some-notes-on-building-and-running-mirage-unikernels-on-cubieboard2/&quot;&gt;&quot;Some Notes on Building and Running Mirage Unikernels on Cubieboard2&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;More than just static sites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites have become the new 'hello world' app. They're simple to manage,
low-risk and provide lots of opportunities to experience something new.  These
aspects make them ideal for discovering the benefits (and trade offs) of the
unikernel approach and I look forward to seeing what variations people come up
with — For instance, there aren't any public instructions for deploying to
Rackspace so it would be great to read about someone's experiences there.
However, there are also many other applications that also fit the above
criteria of simplicity, low risk and plentiful learning opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Leonard decided to create a unikernel for a simple REST service for
queuing package uploads for 0install.  His post takes you from the very
beginning, with a simple hello world program running on Xen, all the way
through to creating his REST service. Along the way there a lots of code
snippets and explanations of the libraries being used and what they're doing.
This is a great use-case for unikernels and there are a lot of interesting
things to take from this post, for example the ease with which Thomas was able
to find and fix bugs using regular tools. There's also lots of information on
performance testing and optimising of the unikernel, which he covers in a
follow-up post, and he even built tools to visualise the traces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas' posts&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hello world and REST service&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://roscidus.com/blog/blog/2014/07/28/my-first-unikernel/&quot;&gt;&quot;My First Unikernel&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiling and optimisations&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://roscidus.com/blog/blog/2014/08/15/optimising-the-unikernel/&quot;&gt;&quot;Optimising the Unikernel&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tool to visualise traces&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;http://roscidus.com/blog/blog/2014/10/27/visualising-an-asynchronous-monad&quot;&gt;&quot;Visualising an Asynchronous Monad&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, there's much more activity out there than described in this post as
people continually propose ideas on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.xenproject.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/mirageos-devel&quot;&gt;Mirage mailing list&lt;/a&gt; — both
for things they would like to try out and issues they came up against. In my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/blog/2014/from-jekyll-site-to-unikernel/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I pointed out that the workflow is applicable to any
type of unikernel and as Thomas showed, with bit of effort it's already
possible to create useful, real-world services using the many libraries that
already exist. There's also a lot of scaffolding in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-skeleton&quot;&gt;mirage-skeleton&lt;/a&gt;
repo that you can build on which makes it even easier to get involved.  If you
want to dive deeper into the libraries and perhaps learn OCaml, there are lots
of &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/learn/books.html&quot;&gt;resources online&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-www/wiki/Pioneer-Projects&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; to get involved with too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is a great time to try building a unikernel for yourself and as you can
see from the posts above, shared experiences help other people progress
further and branch out into new areas. When you've had a chance to try
something out please do share your experiences online!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;This post also appears on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nymote.org/blog/2015/unikernels-for-everyone/&quot;&gt;Nymote blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;!-- ===== LINKS ===== --&gt;



</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Towards a governance framework for OCaml.org</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/towards-governance-framework-for-ocamlorg"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2015-01-08T18:15:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/towards-governance-framework-for-ocamlorg</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The projects around the OCaml.org domain name are becoming more established
and it's time to think about how they're organised. 2014 saw a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of
activity, which built on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/projects/ocamllabs/news/index.html#OnlineatOCamlorg&quot;&gt;successes from 2013&lt;/a&gt;.
Some of the main things that stand out to me are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/contributors.html&quot;&gt;volunteers&lt;/a&gt; contributing to the public website with
translations, bug fixes and content updates, as well as many new visitors —
for example, the new page on &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/learn/teaching-ocaml.html&quot;&gt;teaching OCaml&lt;/a&gt; received over 5k
visits alone. The increasing contributions are a result of the earlier work on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/announcing-new-ocamlorg/&quot;&gt;re-engineering the site&lt;/a&gt; and there are many ways to get involved
so please do &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/labels/contribute%21&quot;&gt;contribute&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 10px&quot; src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/web/opampkg-2015-01-08.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relentless improvements and growth of OPAM, both in terms of the
repository — with over 1000 additional packages and several
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/pipermail/opam-devel/2014-October/000781.html&quot;&gt;new repo maintainers&lt;/a&gt; — and also improved workflows (e.g the new
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/blog/opam-1-2-pin/&quot;&gt;pin functionality&lt;/a&gt;).
The OPAM site and package list also moved to the ocaml.org domain, becoming
the substrate for the OCaml Platform efforts. This began with the work towards
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/blog/opam-1-2-0-beta4/&quot;&gt;OPAM 1.2&lt;/a&gt; and there is much more to come (including closer
integration in terms of styling). Join the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/platform&quot;&gt;Platform list&lt;/a&gt; to
keep up to date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much more activity on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org&quot;&gt;mailing lists&lt;/a&gt; in general and user groups
requesting to have lists made (e.g the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/teaching&quot;&gt;teaching list&lt;/a&gt;). If anyone
has a need for a new list, just ask on the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/infrastructure&quot;&gt;infrastructure list&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is other work besides those I've mentioned and I think by any measure,
all the projects have been quite successful. As the community continues to
develop, it's important to clarify how things currently work to improve the
level of transparency and make it easier for newcomers to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Factors for a governance framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last couple of months, I've been looking over how larger projects
manage themselves and the governance documents that are available. My aim has
been to put such a document together for the OCaml.org domain without
introducing burdensome processes.  There are number of things that stood out
to me during this process, which have guided the approach I'm taking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My considerations for an OCaml.org governance document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A governance document is not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for success but it's valuable to
demonstrate a commitment to a &lt;strong&gt;stable decision-making process&lt;/strong&gt;.  There are
many projects that progress perfectly well without any documented processes
and indeed the work around OCaml.org so far is a good example of this (as well
as OCaml itself).  However, for projects to achieve a scale greater than the
initial teams, it's a significant benefit to encode in writing how things work
(NB: please note that I didn't define the &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; of decision-making process -
merely that it's a stable one).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It must &lt;strong&gt;clarify its scope&lt;/strong&gt; so that there is no confusion about what the
document covers. In the case of OCaml.org, it needs to be clear that the
governance covers the domain itself, rather than referring to the website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should &lt;strong&gt;document the reality&lt;/strong&gt;, rather than represent an aspirational
goal or what people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; a governance structure should look like.  It's
very tempting to think of an idealised structure without recognising that
behaviours and norms have &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; been established. Sometimes this will be
vague and poorly defined but that might simply indicate areas that the
community hasn't encountered yet (e.g it's uncommon for any new project to
seriously think about dispute resolution processes until they have to).  In
this sense, the initial version of a governance document should simply be a
written description of how things currently stand, rather than a means to
adjust that behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should be &lt;strong&gt;simple and self-contained&lt;/strong&gt;, so that anyone can understand
the intent quickly without recourse to other documents.  It may be tempting to
consider every edge-case or try to resolve every likely ambiguity but this
just leads to large, legal documents.  This approach may well be necessary
once projects have reached a certain scale but to implement it sooner would be
a case of premature optimisation — not to mention that very few people would
read and remember such a document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a &lt;strong&gt;living document&lt;/strong&gt;. If the community decides that it would prefer a
new arrangement, then the document conveniently provides a stable starting
point from which to iterate. Indeed, it &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; adapt along with the project
that it governs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With the above points in mind, I've been putting together a draft governance
framework to cover how the OCaml.org domain name is managed.  It's been a
quiet work-in-progress for some time and I'll be getting in touch with
maintainers of specific projects soon.  Once I've had a round of reviews, I'll
be sharing it more widely and posting it here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- [![FIGURE 06.1 Governance versus anarchy on Flickr](http://amirchaudhry.com/images/web/governance-alpha.png)](https://www.flickr.com/photos/jurgenappelo/5201270923/) --&gt;

</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Writing Planet in pure OCaml</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/writing-planet-in-pure-ocaml"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2014-04-29T10:30:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/writing-planet-in-pure-ocaml</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been learning OCaml for some time now but not really had a problem that
I wanted to solve. As such, my progress has been rather slow and sporadic
and I only make time for exercises when I'm travelling. In order to focus my
learning, I have to identify and tackle something specific. That's usually
the best way to advance and I recently found something I can work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I've been trying to write more blog posts, I want to be able to keep as
much content on my own site as possible and syndicate my posts out to other
sites I run. Put simply, I want to be able to take multiple feeds from
different sources and merge them into one feed, which will be served from
some other site. In addition, I also want to render that feed as HTML on a
webpage. All of this has to remain within the OCaml toolchain so it can be
used as part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org/&quot;&gt;Mirage&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. I can use it when
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/from-jekyll-to-unikernel-in-fifty-lines&quot;&gt;building unikernels&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I'm describing might sound familiar and there's a well-known tool that
does this called &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planet_(software)&quot;&gt;Planet&lt;/a&gt;. It's a 'river of news' feed reader, which
aggregates feeds and can display posts on webpages and you can find the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.planetplanet.org&quot;&gt;original Planet&lt;/a&gt; and it's successor &lt;a href=&quot;http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/docs/index.html&quot;&gt;Venus&lt;/a&gt;, both written in Python.
However, Venus seems to be unmaintained as there are a number of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rubys/venus/issues&quot;&gt;unresolved issues and pull requests&lt;/a&gt;, which have been
languishing for quite some time with no discussion. There does appear to be
a more active Ruby implementation called &lt;a href=&quot;http://feedreader.github.io/&quot;&gt;Pluto&lt;/a&gt;, with recent commits and
no reported issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- 
    \[Rant: Frankly, the naming of these versions leaves a lot to be desired.
    When you know exactly what you're supposed to Google for you're fine, but
    until then you're just on a random-walk through space websites. I'm
    lucky I managed to get to the Wikipedia page.\] 
--&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Benefits of a Planet in pure OCaml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I could use the one of the above options, it would be much more
useful to keep everything within the OCaml ecosystem.  This way I can make
the best use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=2566628&quot;&gt;unikernel approach&lt;/a&gt; with Mirage (i.e lean,
single-purpose appliances). Obviously, the existing options don't lend
themselves to this approach and there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://forge.ocamlcore.org/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;amp;aid=1349&amp;amp;group_id=1&amp;amp;atid=101&quot;&gt;known bugs&lt;/a&gt; as a lot has
changed on the web since Planet Venus (e.g the adoption of HTML5).
Having said that, I can learn a lot from the existing implementations and
I'm glad I'm not embarking into completely uncharted territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the OCaml version doesn't need to (and &lt;em&gt;shouldn't&lt;/em&gt;) be written
as one monolithic library.  Instead, pulling together a collection of
smaller, reusable libraries that present clear interfaces to each other
would make things much more maintainable. This would bring substantially
greater benefits to everyone and &lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/&quot;&gt;OPAM&lt;/a&gt; can manage the dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
    OPAM makes managing dependencies easy so having a number of single-
    purpose libraries is A Good Thing and costs almost nothing.  This 
    approach has already worked well with examples like an [IP address 
    library][ipaddr] and the [OCaml markdown library][OMD], which can be 
    used by multiple projects.
--&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Breaking down the problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first cut is somewhat straightforward as we have a piece that deals with
the consumption and manipulation of feeds and another that takes the result
and emits HTML. This is also how the original Planet is put together, with a
library called &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/feedparser/&quot;&gt;feedparser&lt;/a&gt; and another for templating pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the feed-parsing aspect, I can break it down further by considering Atom
and RSS feeds separately and then even further by thinking about how to (1)
consume such feeds and (2) output them. Then there is the HTML component,
where it may be necessary to consider existing representations of HTML. These
are not new ideas and since I'm claiming that individual pieces might be
useful then it's worth finding out which ones are already available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Existing components&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to find existing libraries is via the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/packages&quot;&gt;OPAM package list&lt;/a&gt;. Some quick searches for &lt;code&gt;RSS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;XML&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;HTML&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;net&lt;/code&gt; bring up a lot of packages. The most relevant of these seem to be
&lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/xmlm/xmlm.1.2.0/&quot;&gt;xmlm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/ocamlrss/ocamlrss.2.2.2/&quot;&gt;ocamlrss&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/cow/cow.0.9.1/&quot;&gt;cow&lt;/a&gt; and maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/packages/xmldiff/xmldiff.0.1/&quot;&gt;xmldiff&lt;/a&gt;. I noticed that
nothing appears, when searching for &lt;code&gt;Atom&lt;/code&gt;, but I do know that &lt;code&gt;cow&lt;/code&gt; has an
Atom module for creating feeds. In terms of turning feeds into pages and
HTML, I'm aware of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/blob/master/script/rss2html.ml&quot;&gt;rss2html&lt;/a&gt; used on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt; website and parts of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/packages/ocamlnet/ocamlnet.3.7.3/&quot;&gt;ocamlnet&lt;/a&gt; that may be relevant (e.g &lt;code&gt;nethtml&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;netstring&lt;/code&gt;) as well as
&lt;code&gt;cow&lt;/code&gt;.  There is likely to be other code I'm missing but this is useful as a
first pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, a number of components are already out there but it's not obvious
if they're compatible (e.g html) and there are still gaps (e.g atom). Since
I also want to minimise dependencies, I'll try and use whatever works but
may ultimately have to roll my own. Either way, I can learn from what
already exists. Perhaps I'm being overconfident but if I can break things
down sensibly and keep the scope constrained then this should be an
achievable project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The first (baby) steps - an Atom parser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is an exercise for me to learn OCaml by solving a problem, I need to
break it down into bite-size pieces and take each one at a time. Practically
speaking, this means limiting the scope to be as narrow as possible while
still producing a useful result &lt;em&gt;for me&lt;/em&gt;.  That last part is important as I
have specific needs and it's likely that the first thing I make won't be
particularly interesting for many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my specific use-case, I'm only interested in dealing with Atom feeds as
that's what I use on my site and others I'm involved with. Initial feedback
is that creating an Atom parser will be the bulk of the work and I should
start by defining the types. To keep this manageable, I'm only going to deal
with my own feeds instead of attempting a fully compliant parser (in other
words, I'll only consider the subset of &lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287&quot;&gt;RFC4287&lt;/a&gt; that's relevant to me).
Once I can parse, merge and write such feeds I should be able to iterate
from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make my requirements more concrete:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only consider &lt;em&gt;my own&lt;/em&gt; Atom feeds for now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initially, be able to parse and emit just one Atom feed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then be able to merge 2+ feeds, specifically:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use tag-based feeds from my personal site as starting points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be able to de-dupe content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No database or storage (construct it afresh every time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimise library dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;!-- 
    Perhaps these requirements are already too much and I may decide to dial
    it down even further (e.g just figure out how to consume *one* feed),
    but I won't really know until I get started. For example, I can imagine
    that I'll need one bunch of code to deal with Atom feeds and then
    perhaps I can make another (feedparser), that depends on it and others
    to deal with general feeds.
--&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Timeframes and workflow&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've honestly no idea how long this might take and I'm treating it as a
side-project. I know there are many people out there who could produce a
working version of everything in a week or two but I'm not one of them (yet).
There are also &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of ancillary things I need to learn on the way, like
packaging, improving my knowledge of Git and dealing with build systems. If
I had to put a vague time frame on this, I'd be thinking in months rather
than weeks.  It might even be the case that others start work on parts of
this and ship things sooner but that's great as I'll probably be able to use
whatever they create and move further along the chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of workflow, everything will be done in the open, warts and all, and
I expect to make embarrassing mistakes as I go. You can follow along on my
freshly created &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amirmc/ocamlatom&quot;&gt;OCaml Atom&lt;/a&gt; repo, and I'll be using the issue tracker as
the main way of dealing with bugs and features. Let the fun begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- acknowledgements --&gt;


&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/em&gt; Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://erratique.ch&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ashishagarwal.org&quot;&gt;Ashish&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Chris00&quot;&gt;Christophe&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://philippewang.info/&quot;&gt;Philippe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gazagnaire.org&quot;&gt;Thomas&lt;/a&gt; for discussions on an earlier draft of this post
and providing feedback on my approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- links --&gt;



</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>From Jekyll site to Unikernel in fifty lines of code.</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/from-jekyll-to-unikernel-in-fifty-lines"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2014-03-10T18:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/from-jekyll-to-unikernel-in-fifty-lines</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org&quot;&gt;Mirage&lt;/a&gt; has reached a point where it's possible to easily set up
end-to-end toolchains to build &lt;a href=&quot;http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=2566628&quot;&gt;unikernels&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;!--\[If you're not sure what that is, read the post [What is a unikernel?][amc-unikernel]\]--&gt;
My first use-case is to be able to generate a unikernel which can serve my
personal static site but to do it with as much automation as possible. It
turns out this is possible with less than 50 lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Jekyll and GitHub Pages at the moment so I wanted a workflow that's as
easy to use, though I'm happy to spend some time up front to set up and
configure things.
The tools for achieving what I want are in good shape so
this post takes the example of a Jekyll site (i.e this one) and goes through
the steps to produce a unikernel on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org&quot;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt; (a continuous integration service) which can later be
deployed.  Many of these instructions already exist in various forms but
they're collated here to aid this use-case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will take you, dear reader, through the process and when we're finished,
the workflow will be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You'll write your posts on your local machine as normal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A push to GitHub will trigger a unikernel build for each commit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Xen unikernel will be pushed to a repo for deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, we'll first check that we can build a unikernel VM locally,
then we'll set up a continuous integration service to automatically build
them for us and finally we'll adapt the CI service to also deploy the built
VM.  Although the amount of code required is small, each of these steps is
covered below in some detail.
For simplicity, I'll assume you already have OCaml and Opam
installed -- if not, you can find out how via the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://realworldocaml.org/install&quot;&gt;Real Word OCaml install instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building locally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that the build actually works, you should run things locally at
least once before pushing to Travis.  It's worth noting that the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-skeleton&quot;&gt;mirage-skeleton&lt;/a&gt; repo contains a lot of useful, public domain examples
and helpfully, the specific code we need is in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-skeleton/tree/master/static_website&quot;&gt;mirage-skeleton/static_website&lt;/a&gt;.  Copy both the &lt;code&gt;config.ml&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;dispatch.ml&lt;/code&gt; files from that folder into a new &lt;code&gt;_mirage&lt;/code&gt; folder in your
jekyll repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit &lt;code&gt;config.ml&lt;/code&gt; so that the two mentions of &lt;code&gt;./htdocs&lt;/code&gt; are replaced with
&lt;code&gt;../_site&lt;/code&gt;.  This is the only change you'll need to make and you should now
be able to build the unikernel with the unix backend.  Make sure you have
the mirage package installed by running &lt;code&gt;$ opam install mirage&lt;/code&gt; and then run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(edit: If you already have &lt;code&gt;mirage&lt;/code&gt;, remember to &lt;code&gt;opam update&lt;/code&gt; to make sure you've got the latest packages.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;_mirage
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;mirage configure --unix
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;make depend         &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# needed as of mirage 1.2 onward&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;mirage build
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ..&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's all it takes!  In a few minutes there will be a unikernel built on
your system (symlinked as &lt;code&gt;_mirage/mir-www&lt;/code&gt;).  If there are any errors, make
sure that Opam is up to date and that you have the latest version of the
static_website files from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-skeleton&quot;&gt;mirage-skeleton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Serving the site locally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to see this site locally, you can do so from within the
&lt;code&gt;_mirage&lt;/code&gt; folder by running unikernel you just built.  There's more
information about the details of this on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://openmirage.org/wiki/mirage-www&quot;&gt;Mirage docs site&lt;/a&gt;
but the quick instructions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;_mirage
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;sudo mirage run

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# in another terminal window&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;sudo ifconfig tap0 10.0.0.1 255.255.255.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can now point your browser at http://10.0.0.2/ and see your site!
Once you're finished browsing, &lt;code&gt;$ mirage clean&lt;/code&gt; will clear up all the
generated files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the build is working locally, we can set up a continuous integration
system to perform the builds for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Setting up Travis CI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 10px&quot; src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/jekyll-unikernel/travis.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We'll be using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org&quot;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt; service, which is free for open-source
projects (so this assumes you're using a public repo).  The benefit of using
Travis is that you can build a unikernel &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; needing a local OCaml
environment, but it's always quicker to debug things locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Log in to Travis using your GitHub ID which will then trigger a scan of your
repositories.  When this is complete, go to your Travis accounts page and
find the repo you'll be building the unikernel from.  Switch it 'on' and
Travis will automatically set your GitHub post-commit hook and token for you.
That's all you need to do on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you next make a push to your repository, GitHub will inform Travis,
which will then look for a YAML file in the root of the repo called
&lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt;.  That file describes what Travis should do and what the build
matrix is.  Since OCaml is not one of the supported languages, we'll be
writing our build script manually (this is actually easier than it sounds).
First, let's set up the YAML file and then we'll examine the build script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Travis YAML file - .travis.yml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.travis-ci.com/user/ci-environment/#CI-environment-OS&quot;&gt;Travis CI environment&lt;/a&gt; is based on Ubuntu 12.04, with a
number of things pre-installed (e.g Git, networking tools etc).  Travis
doesn't support OCaml (yet) so we'll use the &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; environment to get the
packages we need, specifically, the OCaml compiler, Opam and Mirage. Once
those are set up, our build should run pretty much the same as it did locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, let's keep things simple and only focus on the latest releases
(OCaml 4.01.0 and Opam 1.1.1), which means our build matrix is very simple.
The build instructions will be in the file &lt;code&gt;_mirage/travis.sh&lt;/code&gt;, which we
will move to and trigger from the &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.  This means our YAML
file should look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;before_script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;cd _mirage&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;bash -ex travis.sh&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;env&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;matrix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;MIRAGE_BACKEND=xen DEPLOY=0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;MIRAGE_BACKEND=unix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The matrix enables us to have parallel builds for different environments and
this one is very simple as it's only building two unikernels. One worker
will build for the Xen backend and another worker will build for the Unix
backend. The &lt;code&gt;_mirage/travis.sh&lt;/code&gt; script will clarify what each of these
environments translates to.  We'll come back to the &lt;code&gt;DEPLOY&lt;/code&gt; flag later on
(it's not necessary yet).  Now that this file is set up, we can work on the
build script itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The build script - travis.sh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To save time, we'll be using an Ubuntu PPA to quickly get
&lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/~avsm&quot;&gt;pre-packaged versions of the OCaml compiler and Opam&lt;/a&gt;, so the
first thing to do is define which PPAs each line of the build matrix
corresponds to.  Since we're keeping things simple, we only need one PPA
that has the most recent releases of OCaml and Opam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;ppa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;avsm/ocaml41+opam11
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;yes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sudo add-apt-repository ppa:&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ppa&lt;/span&gt;
sudo apt-get update -qq
sudo apt-get install -qq ocaml ocaml-native-compilers camlp4-extra opam&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;[NB: There are many &lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/~avsm&quot;&gt;other PPAs&lt;/a&gt; for different combinations of
OCaml/Opam which are useful for testing].  Once the appropriate PPAs have
been set up it's time to initialise Opam and install Mirage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;OPAMYES&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1
opam init
opam install mirage
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;eval&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;opam config env&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We set &lt;code&gt;OPAMYES=1&lt;/code&gt; to get non-interactive use of Opam (it defaults to 'yes'
for any user input) and if we want full build logs, we could also set
&lt;code&gt;OPAMVERBOSE=1&lt;/code&gt; (I haven't in this example).
The rest should be straight-forward and you'll end up with an
Ubuntu machine with OCaml, Opam and the Mirage package installed.  It's now
trivial to do the next step of actually building the unikernel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;mirage configure --&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$MIRAGE_BACKEND&lt;/span&gt;
mirage build&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see how we've used the environment variable from the Travis file and
this is where our two parallel builds begin to diverge.  When you've saved
this file, you'll need to change permissions to make it executable by doing
&lt;code&gt;$ chmod +x _mirage/travis.sh&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's all you need to build the unikernel on Travis!  You should now commit
both the YAML file and the build script to the repo and push the changes to
GitHub.  Travis should automatically start your first build and you can
watch the console output online to check that both the Xen and Unix backends
complete properly.  If you notice any errors, you should go back over your
build script and fix it before the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Deploying your unikernel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 10px&quot; src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/jekyll-unikernel/octocat.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Travis has finished its builds it will simply destroy the worker and
all its contents, including the unikernels we just built.  This is perfectly
fine for testing but if we want to also &lt;em&gt;deploy&lt;/em&gt; a unikernel, we need to get
it out of the Travis worker after it's built. In this case, we want to
extract the Xen-based unikernel so that we can later start it on a Xen-based
machine (e.g Amazon, Rackspace or - in our case - a machine on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bytemark.co.uk&quot;&gt;Bytemark&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the unikernel VMs are small (only tens of MB), our method for
exporting will be to commit the Xen unikernel into a repository on GitHub.
It can be retrieved and started later on and keeping the VMs in version
control gives us very effective snapshots (we can roll back the site without
having to rebuild).  This is something that would be much more challenging
if we were using the 'standard' web toolstack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deployment step is a little more complex as we have to send the
Travis worker a private SSH key, which will give it push access to a GitHub
repository.  Of course, we don't want to expose that key by simply adding it
to the Travis file so we have to encrypt it somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sending Travis a private SSH key&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travis supports &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.travis-ci.com/user/encryption-keys/&quot;&gt;encrypted environment variables&lt;/a&gt;. Each
repository has its own public key and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubygems.org/gems/travis&quot;&gt;Travis gem&lt;/a&gt; uses
this public key to encrypt data, which you then add to your &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt;
file for decryption by the worker.  This is meant for sending things like
private API tokens and other small amounts of data. Trying to encrypt an SSH
key isn't going to work as it's too large.  Instead we'll use
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/avsm/travis-senv&quot;&gt;travis-senv&lt;/a&gt;, which encodes, encrypts and chunks up the key into smaller
pieces and then reassembles those pieces on the Travis worker.  We still use
the Travis gem to encrypt the pieces to add them to the &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you could give Travis a key that accesses your whole GitHub account, my
preference is to create a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; deploy key, which will only be used for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/managing-deploy-keys#deploy-keys&quot;&gt;deployment to one repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# make a key pair on your local machine&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/.ssh/
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;ssh-keygen -t dsa -C &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;travis.deploy&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -f travis-deploy_dsa
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; -&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that this is a 1024 bit key so if you decide to use a 2048 bit key,
then be aware that Travis &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/avsm/travis-senv/issues/1&quot;&gt;sometimes has issues&lt;/a&gt;. Now that we have
a key, we can encrypt it and add it to the Travis file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# on your local machine&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# install the necessary components&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;gem install travis
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;opam install travis-senv

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# chunk the key, add to yml file and rm the intermediate&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;travis-senv encrypt ~/.ssh/travis-deploy_dsa _travis_env
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cat _travis_env &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; travis encrypt -ps --add
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;rm _travis_env&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;travis-senv&lt;/code&gt; encrypts and chunks the key locally on your machine, placing
its output in a file you decide (&lt;code&gt;_travis_env&lt;/code&gt;).  We then take that output
file and pipe it to the &lt;code&gt;travis&lt;/code&gt; ruby gem, asking it to encrypt the input,
treating each line as separate and to be appended (&lt;code&gt;-ps&lt;/code&gt;) and then actually
adding that to the Travis file (&lt;code&gt;--add&lt;/code&gt;).  You can run &lt;code&gt;$ travis encrypt -h&lt;/code&gt;
to understand these options.  Once you've run the above commands,
&lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; will look as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;before_script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;cd _mirage&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;bash -ex travis.sh&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;env&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;matrix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;MIRAGE_BACKEND=xen DEPLOY=0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;MIRAGE_BACKEND=unix&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;secure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;....&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;encrypted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;....&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;secure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;....&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;encrypted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;....&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;secure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p-Indicator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;....&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;encrypted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;....&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;l-Scalar-Plain&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The number of secure variables added depends on the type and size of the key
you had to chunk, so it could vary from 8 up to 29. We'll commit
these additions later on, alongside additions to the build script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we also need to make a repository on GitHub
and add the public deploy key so
that Travis can push to it.  Once you've created your repo and added a
README, follow GitHub's instructions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/managing-deploy-keys#deploy-keys&quot;&gt;adding deploy keys&lt;/a&gt;
and paste in the public key (i.e. the content of &lt;code&gt;travis-deploy_dsa.pub&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we can securely pass a private SSH key to the worker
and have a repo that the worker can push to, we need to
make additions to the build script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Committing the unikernel to a repository&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we can set &lt;code&gt;DEPLOY=1&lt;/code&gt; in the YAML file we only need to make
additions to the build script.  Specifically, we want to assure that: only
the Xen backend is deployed; only &lt;em&gt;pushes&lt;/em&gt; to the repo result in
deployments, not pull requests (we do still want &lt;em&gt;builds&lt;/em&gt; for pull requests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the build script (&lt;code&gt;_mirage/travis.sh&lt;/code&gt;), which is being run by the worker,
we'll have to reconstruct the SSH key and configure Git.  In addition,
Travis gives us a set of useful &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.travis-ci.com/user/ci-environment/#Environment-variables&quot;&gt;environment variables&lt;/a&gt; so we'll
use the latest commit hash (&lt;code&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/code&gt;) to name the the VM (which also
helps us trace which commit it was built from).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's easier to consider this section of code at once so I've explained the
details in the comments. This section is what you need to add at the end of
your existing build script (i.e straight after &lt;code&gt;mirage build&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Only deploy if the following conditions are met.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;$MIRAGE_BACKEND&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;xen&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
            -a &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;$DEPLOY&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
            -a &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;$TRAVIS_PULL_REQUEST&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# The Travis worker will already have access to the chunks&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# passed in via the yaml file. Now we need to reconstruct &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# the GitHub SSH key from those and set up the config file.&lt;/span&gt;
    opam install travis-senv
    mkdir -p ~/.ssh
    travis-senv decrypt &amp;gt; ~/.ssh/id_dsa &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This doesn&amp;#39;t expose it&lt;/span&gt;
    chmod &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;600&lt;/span&gt; ~/.ssh/id_dsa             &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Owner can read and write&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Host some_user github.com&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;   &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/config
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;  Hostname github.com&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;          &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/config
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;  StrictHostKeyChecking no&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;     &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/config
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;  CheckHostIP no&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;               &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/config
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;  UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/config

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Configure the worker&amp;#39;s git details&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# otherwise git actions will fail.&lt;/span&gt;
    git config --global user.email &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;user@example.com&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    git config --global user.name &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Travis Build Bot&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Do the actual work for deployment.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Clone the deployment repo. Notice the user,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# which is the same as in the ~/.ssh/config file.&lt;/span&gt;
    git clone git@some_user:amirmc/www-test-deploy
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;www-test-deploy

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Make a folder named for the commit. &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# If we&amp;#39;re rebuiling a VM from a previous&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# commit, then we need to clear the old one.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Then copy in both the config file and VM.&lt;/span&gt;
    rm -rf &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt;
    mkdir -p &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt;
    cp ../mir-www.xen ../config.ml &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Compress the VM and add a text file to note&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# the commit of the most recently built VM.&lt;/span&gt;
    bzip2 -9 &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt;/mir-www.xen
    git pull --rebase
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; latest    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# update ref to most recent&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Add, commit and push the changes!&lt;/span&gt;
    git add &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$TRAVIS_COMMIT&lt;/span&gt; latest
    git commit -m &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;adding $TRAVIS_COMMIT built for $MIRAGE_BACKEND&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    git push origin master
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Go out and enjoy the Sun!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point you should commit the changes to &lt;code&gt;./travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; (don't forget
the deploy flag) and &lt;code&gt;_mirage/travis.sh&lt;/code&gt; and push the changes to GitHub.
Everything else will take place automatically and in a few minutes you will
have a unikernel ready to deploy on top of Xen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see both the complete YAML file and build script in use on my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amirmc/www-test&quot;&gt;test repo&lt;/a&gt;, as well as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org/amirmc/www-test&quot;&gt;build logs&lt;/a&gt; for that repo
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amirmc/www-test-deploy&quot;&gt;deploy repo&lt;/a&gt; with a VM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Pro-tip: If you add &lt;/em&gt;&lt;code&gt;[skip ci]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;em&gt; anywhere in your
commit message, Travis will skip the build for that commit.
This is very useful if you're making minor changes, like updating a
README.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Finishing up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I'm still using Jekyll for my website, I made a short script in my
jekyll repository (&lt;code&gt;_deploy-unikernel.sh&lt;/code&gt;) that builds the site, commits the
contents of &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; and pushes to GitHub. I simply run this after I've
committed a new blog post and the rest takes care of itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash&lt;/span&gt;
jekyll build
git add _site
git commit -m &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;update _site&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! You now have an end-to-end workflow that will produce a
unikernel VM from your Jekyll-based site and push it to a repo.  If you
strip out all the comments, you'll see that we've written less than 50 lines
of code! Admittedly, I'm not counting the 80 or so lines that came for free
in the &lt;code&gt;*.ml&lt;/code&gt; files but that's still pretty impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we still need a machine to take that VM and run it but that's a
topic for another post.  For the time-being, I'm still using GitHub Pages
but once the VM is hosted somewhere, I will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn off GitHub Pages and serve from the VM -- but still using Jekyll in
the workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace Jekyll with OCaml-based static-site generation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although all the tools already exist to switch now, I'm taking my time so
that I can easily maintain the code I end up using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Expanding the script for testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that the examples here are not very flexible or
extensible but that was a deliberate choice to keep them readable.  It's
possible to do much more with the build matrix and script, as you can see
from the Travis files on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amirmc/amirmc.github.com/tree/master/_mirage&quot;&gt;website repo&lt;/a&gt;, which were based on
those of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-www&quot;&gt;Mirage site&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mor1/mort-www&quot;&gt;Mort's site&lt;/a&gt;.
Specifically, you can note the use of more environment variables and case
statements to decide which PPAs to grab.  Once you've got your builds
working, it's worth improving your scripts to make them more maintainable
and cover the test cases you feel are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Not just for static sites (surprise!)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have noticed that in very few places in the toolchain above have I
mentioned anything specific to static sites per se.  The workflow is simply
(1) do some stuff locally, (2) push to a continuous integration service
which then (3) builds and deploys a Xen-based unikernel.  Apart from the
convenient folder structure, the specific work to treat this as a static
site lives in the &lt;code&gt;*.ml&lt;/code&gt; files, which I've skipped over for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the GitHub+Travis workflow we've developed here is quite general
and will apply to almost &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; unikernels that we may want to construct.
I encourage you to explore the examples in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-skeleton&quot;&gt;mirage-skeleton&lt;/a&gt; repo and
keep your build script maintainable.  We'll be using it again the next time
we build unikernel devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/em&gt; There were lots of things I read over while writing this
post but there were a few particularly useful things that you should look up.
Anil's posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://anil.recoil.org/2013/09/30/travis-and-ocaml.html&quot;&gt;Testing with Travis&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://anil.recoil.org/2013/10/06/travis-secure-ssh-integration.html&quot;&gt;Travis for secure deployments&lt;/a&gt; are quite succinct (and
were themselves prompted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.mlin.net/2013/02/testing-ocaml-projects-on-travis-ci.html&quot;&gt;Mike Lin's Travis post&lt;/a&gt; several
months earlier). Looking over Mort's &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mor1/mort-www/blob/master/.travis-build.sh&quot;&gt;build script&lt;/a&gt; and that of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mirage/mirage-www/blob/master/.travis-ci.sh&quot;&gt;mirage-www&lt;/a&gt; helped me figure out the deployment steps as well as improve
my own script. Special thanks also to &lt;a href=&quot;http://erratique.ch&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lpw25.net&quot;&gt;Leo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://anil.recoil.org&quot;&gt;Anil&lt;/a&gt; for
commenting on an earlier draft of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Switching from Bootstrap to Zurb Foundation</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/switching-from-bootstrap-to-zurb-foundation"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-11-26T21:05:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/switching-from-bootstrap-to-zurb-foundation</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've just updated my site's HTML/CSS and moved from Twitter Bootstrap to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.zurb.com/learn/features.html&quot;&gt;Zurb Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.  This post captures my subjective notes on the
migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;My use of Bootstrap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I originally set this site up, I didn't know what frameworks existed or
anything more than the basics of dealing with HTML (and barely any CSS).  I
came across Twitter Bootstrap and immediately decided it would Solve All My
Problems.  It really did.  Since then, I've gone through one 'upgrade' with
Bootstrap (from 1.x to 2.x), after which I dutifully ignored all the fixes
and improvements (note that Bootstrap was up to v2.3.2 while I was still
using v2.0.2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/switch-to-foundation/responsive-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;Responsive Design&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, this was fine with me but for a while now, I've been
meaning to make this site 'responsive' (read: not look like crap from a
mobile).  Bootstrap v3 purports to be mobile-first so upgrading would likely
give me what I'm after but v3 is &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/getting-started/&quot;&gt;not backwards compatible&lt;/a&gt;,
meaning I'd have to rewrite parts of the HTML.  Since this step was
unavoidable, it led me to have another look at front-end frameworks, just to
see if I was missing anything.  This was especially relevant since we'd
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/announcing-new-ocamlorg/&quot;&gt;just released&lt;/a&gt; the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml.org&lt;/a&gt;
website, itself built with Bootstrap v2.3.1 (we'd done the design/templating
work long before v3 was released).  It would be useful to know what else is
out there for any future work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time I discovered Zurb Foundation and also the numerous
comparisons between them (note: Foundation seems to come out ahead in most
of those).  A few days ago, the folks at Zurb released
&lt;a href=&quot;http://zurb.com/article/1280/foundation-5-blasts-off--2&quot;&gt;version 5&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided that now is the time to kick the
tires.  For the last few days, I've been playing with the framework and in
the end I decided to migrate my site over completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.zurb.com/learn/features.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/switch-to-foundation/zurb-yeti.png&quot; alt=&quot;Foundation's Yeti&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Swapping out one framework for another&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I've become moderately experienced with HTML/CSS and I can
usually wrangle things to look the way I want, but my solutions aren't
necessarily elegant. I was initially concerned that I'd already munged
things so much that changing anything would be a pain.  When I first put the
styles for this site together, I had to spend quite a bit of time
overwriting Bootstrap's defaults so I was prepared for the same when using
Foundation.  Turns out that I was fine.  I currently use &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; (and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;) so I only had three template files and a couple of
HTML pages to edit and because I'd kept most of my custom CSS in a separate
file, it was literally a case of swapping out one framework for another and
bug-fixing from there onwards.  There's definitely a lesson here in using
automation as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customising the styles was another area of concern but I was pleasantly
surprised to find I needed &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; customisation than with Bootstrap.  This
is likely because I didn't have to override as many defaults (and probably
because I've learned more about CSS since then).  The one thing I seemed to
be missing was a way to deal with code sections, so I just took what
Bootstrap had and copied it in.  At some point I should revisit this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did take me a while to get my head around Foundation's grid but it was
worth it in the end.  The idea is that you should design for small screens
first and then adjust things for larger screens as necessary. There are
several different default sizes which inherit their properties from the size
below, unless you explicitly override them.  I initially screwed this up by
explicitly defining the grid using the &lt;code&gt;small-#&lt;/code&gt; classes, which obviously
looks ridiculous on small screens.  I fixed it by swapping out &lt;code&gt;small-#&lt;/code&gt; for
&lt;code&gt;medium-#&lt;/code&gt; everywhere in the HTML, after which everything looked reasonable.
Items flowed sensibly into a default column for the small screens and looked
acceptable for larger screens and perfectly fine on desktops.  I could do
more styling of the mobile view but I'd already achieved most of what I was
after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Fixing image galleries and embedded content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only additional thing I used from Bootstrap was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/javascript/#carousel&quot;&gt;Carousel&lt;/a&gt;. I'd
written some custom helper scripts that would take some images and
thumbnails from a specified folder and produce clickable thumbnails with a
slider underneath.  Foundation provides &lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.zurb.com/docs/components/orbit.html&quot;&gt;Orbit&lt;/a&gt;, so I had to spend time
rewriting my script to produce the necessary HTML.  This actually resulted
in cleaner HTML and one of the features I wanted (the ability to link to a
specific image) was available by default in Orbit.  At this point I also
tried to make the output look better for the case where JavaScript is
disabled (in essence, each image is just displayed as a list).  Below is an
example of an image gallery, taken from a previous post, when I
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/joined-the-computer-lab/&quot;&gt;joined the computer lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
  &lt;noscript&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The gallery needs JavaScript but I've tried to make it degrade gracefully. -Amir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;inline-list&quot;&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a data-orbit-link=&quot;join-comp-lab-1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-thumb-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-thumb-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a data-orbit-link=&quot;join-comp-lab-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-thumb-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-thumb-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a data-orbit-link=&quot;join-comp-lab-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-thumb-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-thumb-3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
  &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;ul data-orbit data-options=&quot;next_on_click:true; timer_speed:3000; pause_on_hover:false; bullets:false;&quot;&gt;
    
    &lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image&quot; data-orbit-slide=&quot;join-comp-lab-1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    &lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image&quot; data-orbit-slide=&quot;join-comp-lab-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
    &lt;li class=&quot;gallery-image&quot; data-orbit-slide=&quot;join-comp-lab-3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/join-comp-lab/join-comp-lab-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;join-comp-lab-3&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Foundation also provides a component called &lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.zurb.com/docs/components/flex_video.html&quot;&gt;Flex Video&lt;/a&gt;, which allows the
browser to scale videos to the appropriate size.  This fix was as simple as
going back through old posts and wrapping anything that was &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in a
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&quot;flex-video&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  It really was that simple and all the Vimeo and
YouTube items scaled perfectly.  Here's an example of a video from an
earlier post, where I gave a &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/wireframe-demos-for-ocamlorg/&quot;&gt;walkthrough of the ocaml.org site&lt;/a&gt;.
Try changing the width of your browser window to see it scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flex-video widescreen vimeo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768157?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=de9e6a&quot; width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;303&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Video demo&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Framework differences&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the main difference between the two frameworks is that Bootstrap
uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesscss.org&quot;&gt;LESS&lt;/a&gt; to manage its CSS whereas Foundation uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com&quot;&gt;SASS&lt;/a&gt;.  Frankly,
I've no experience with either of them so it makes little difference to me.
It's worth bearing in mind for anyone who's workflow does involve
pre-processing.  Also, Bootstrap is available under the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/getting-started/#license-faqs&quot;&gt;Apache 2 License&lt;/a&gt;, while Foundation is released under
the &lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.zurb.com/learn/faq.html#question-3&quot;&gt;MIT license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Summary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the transition was pretty painless and most of the time was spent
getting familiar with the grid, hunting for docs/examples and trying to make
the image gallery work the way I wanted.  I do think Bootstrap's docs are
better but Foundation's aren't bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this isn't meant to be a comparison, I much prefer Foundation to
Bootstrap.  If you're not sure which to use then I think the secret is in
the names of the frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bootstrap (for me) was a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; way to '&lt;em&gt;bootstrap&lt;/em&gt;' a site quickly with
lots of acceptable defaults -- it was quick to get started but took some
work to alter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foundation seems to provide a great '&lt;em&gt;foundation&lt;/em&gt;' on which to create more
customised sites -- it's more flexible but needs more upfront thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's pretty much how I'd recommend them to people now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Announcing the new OCaml.org</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/announcing-new-ocamlorg"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-11-20T23:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/announcing-new-ocamlorg</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As some of you may have noticed, the new OCaml.org site is now live!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DNS may still be propagating so if &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;http://ocaml.org&lt;/a&gt; hasn't updated for you then try http://166.78.252.20.  This post is in two parts: the first is the announcement and the second is a call for content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;New OCaml.org website design!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new site represents a major milestone in the continuing growth of the OCaml ecosystem. It's the culmination of a lot of volunteer work over the last several months and I'd specifically like to thank &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Chris00&quot;&gt;Christophe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ashishagarwal.org&quot;&gt;Ashish&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://philippewang.info/CL/&quot;&gt;Philippe&lt;/a&gt; for their dedication (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/commits/master&quot;&gt;commit logs&lt;/a&gt; speak volumes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/wireframe-demos-for-ocamlorg/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/ann-new-ocamlorg/ocaml-home-wire.png&quot; alt=&quot;OCaml.org Wireframes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began this journey just over 8 months ago with paper, pencils and a lot of ideas. This led to a comprehensive set of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/wireframe-demos-for-ocamlorg/&quot;&gt;wireframes and walk-throughs&lt;/a&gt; of the site, which then developed into a collection of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/wiki/Site-Redesign&quot;&gt;Photoshop mockups&lt;/a&gt;. In turn, these formed the basis for the html templates and style sheets, which we've adapted to fit our needs across the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the design process, we also considered the kind of structure and &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/pipermail/infrastructure/2013-July/000211.html&quot;&gt;workflow we aspired to&lt;/a&gt;, both as maintainers and contributors.  This led us to develop completely new tools for &lt;a href=&quot;http://pw374.github.io/posts/2013-09-05-22-31-26-about-omd.html&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pw374.github.io/posts/2013-10-03-20-35-12-using-mpp-two-different-ways.html&quot;&gt;templating&lt;/a&gt; in OCaml, which are now available in OPAM for the benefit all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on all these things in parallel definitely had it challenges (which I'll write about separately) but the result has been worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/images/ann-new-ocamlorg/ocaml-home-mockup.png&quot; alt=&quot;OCaml.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey is ongoing and we still have many more improvements we hope to make. The site you see today primarily improves upon the design, structure and workflows but in time, we also intend to incorporate more information on packages and documentation. With the new tooling, moving the website forward will become much easier and I hope that more members of the community become involved in the generation and curation of content.  This brings me to the second part of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Call for content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have lots of great content on the website but there are parts that could do with a refresh and gaps that could be filled.  As a community driven site, we need ongoing contributions to ensure that the site best reflects its members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you do commercial work on OCaml then maybe you'd like to add yourself to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/community/support.html&quot;&gt;support page&lt;/a&gt;? Perhaps there are tutorials you can help to complete, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org/learn/tutorials/99problems.html&quot;&gt;99 problems&lt;/a&gt;?  If you're not sure where to begin, there are already a number of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/issues?labels=content&quot;&gt;content issues&lt;/a&gt; you could contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we've gone through a bug-hunt already, feedback on the site is still very welcome.  You can either &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/issues&quot;&gt;create an issue&lt;/a&gt; on the tracker (preferred), or email the infrastructure list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's fantastic how far we've come and I look forward to the next phase!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Migration plan for the OCaml.org redesign</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/migration-plan-ocaml-org"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-11-06T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/migration-plan-ocaml-org</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're close to releasing the new design of ocaml.org but need help from the
OCaml community to identify and fix bugs before we switch next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ashish, Christophe, Philippe and I have been discussing how we should go
about this and below is the plan for migration.  If anyone would like to
discuss any of this, then the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/infrastructure&quot;&gt;infrastructure list&lt;/a&gt; is the best
place to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've made a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/tree/redesign&quot;&gt;new branch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the main ocaml.org repository with
the redesign.  This branch is a fork of the master and we've simply cleaned
up and replayed our git commits there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've built a live version of the new site, which is visible at
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://preview.ocaml.org&quot;&gt;http://preview.ocaml.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - this is rebuilt every few minutes
from the branch mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the course of one week, we ask the community to review the new site
and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/issues&quot;&gt;report any bugs or problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the issue tracker. We &lt;em&gt;triage&lt;/em&gt;
those bugs to identify any blockers and work on those first.  This is the
phase we'll be in from &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After one week (7 days), and after blocking bugs have been fixed, we
&lt;strong&gt;merge the redesign branch&lt;/strong&gt; into the master branch.  This would
effectively present the new site to the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During the above, we would not be able to accept any new pull requests on
the master branch but would be happy to accept them on the new, redesign
branch.  Hence, restricting the time frame to one week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that the above is only intended to merge the &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;toolchain&lt;/em&gt; for the new site.  Specifically, we've created new landing
pages, have new style sheets and have restructured the site's contents as
well as made some new libraries (&lt;a href=&quot;http://pw374.github.io/posts/2013-09-05-22-31-26-about-omd.html&quot;&gt;OMD&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pw374.github.io/posts/2013-10-03-20-39-07-OPAMaging-MPP.html&quot;&gt;MPP&lt;/a&gt;). The new toolchain
means people can write files in markdown, which makes contributing content a
lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the files are on GitHub, people don't even need to clone the site
locally to make simple edits (or even add new pages). Just click the 'Edit
this page' link in the footer to be taken to the right file in the
repository and GitHub's editing and pull request features will allow you to
make changes and submit updates, all from within your browser (see the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/creating-and-editing-files-in-your-repository&quot;&gt;GitHub Article&lt;/a&gt; for details).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still work to be done on adding new features but the above changes
are already a great improvement to the site and are ready to be reviewed by
the OCaml community and merged.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Review of the OCaml FPDays tutorial</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/fpdays-review"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-10-28T12:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/fpdays-review</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fpdays.net/2013/sessions/index.php?session=24&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; margin-top: 10px; margin-left: 10px&quot; src=&quot;/images/web/fpdays-logo.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Last Thursday a bunch of us from the OCaml Labs team gave an OCaml tutorial
at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fpdays.net/2013/sessions/index.php?session=24&quot;&gt;FPDays&lt;/a&gt; conference (an event for people interested in Functional
Programming).  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yallop&quot;&gt;Jeremy&lt;/a&gt; and I led the session with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lpw25.net&quot;&gt;Leo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dsheets&quot;&gt;David&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://philippewang.info/CL/&quot;&gt;Philippe&lt;/a&gt; helping everyone progress and dealing with questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 10px&quot; src=&quot;/images/fpdays2013/fpdays2013-01.jpg&quot;&gt;
It turned out to be by far the &lt;em&gt;most popular session&lt;/em&gt; at the conference with
over 20 people all wanting to get to grips with OCaml!  An excellent turnout
and a great indicator of the interest that's out there, especially when you
offer a hands-on session to people.  This shouldn't be a surprise as we've
had good attendance for the general &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Cambridge-NonDysFunctional-Programmers/&quot;&gt;OCaml meetups&lt;/a&gt; I've run
and also the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocamllabs.github.io/compiler-hacking/2013/09/17/compiler-hacking-july-2013.html&quot;&gt;compiler hacking sessions&lt;/a&gt;, which Jeremy and
Leo have been building up (do sign up if you're interested in either of
those!).  We had a nice surprise for attendees, which were
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galley_proof&quot;&gt;uncorrected proof&lt;/a&gt; copies of Real World OCaml and luckily, we had just
enough to go around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the tutorial itself, Jeremy put together a nice sequence of exercises
and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocamllabs/fpdays-skeleton&quot;&gt;skeleton repo&lt;/a&gt; (with helpful comments in the code) so that people
could dive in quickly.  The event was set up to be really informal and the
rough plan was as following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Installation/Intro&lt;/em&gt; - We checked that people had been able to follow the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/fpdays-ocaml-session/&quot;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt;, which we'd sent them in advance.
We also handed out copies of the book and made sure folks were comfortable
with &lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OPAM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hello world&lt;/em&gt; - A light intro to get people familiar with the OCaml
syntax and installing packages with OPAM. This would also help people to get
familiar with the toolchain, workflow and compilation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monty Hall browser game&lt;/em&gt; - Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocsigen.org/js_of_ocaml/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;js_of_ocaml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we wanted
people to create and run the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Hall_problem&quot;&gt;Monty Hall problem&lt;/a&gt; in their
browser.  This would give people a taste of some real world interaction by
having to deal with the DOM and interfaces.  If folks did well, they could
add code to keep logs of the game results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Client-server game&lt;/em&gt; - The previous game was all in the browser (so could
be examined by players) so here the task was to split it into a client and
server, ensuring the two stay in sync.  This would demonstrate the
re-usability of the OCaml code already written and give people a feel for
client server interactions. If people wanted to do more, they could use
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/pkg/ctypes/0.1.1/&quot;&gt;ctypes&lt;/a&gt; and get better random numbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We did manage to stick to the overall scheme as above and we think this is a
great base from which to improve future tutorials.  It has the really nice
benefit of having visual, interactive elements and the ability to run things
both in the browser as well as on the server is a great way to show the
versatility of OCaml.  &lt;code&gt;js_of_ocaml&lt;/code&gt; is quite a mature tool and so it's
no surprise that it's also used by companies such as Facebook (see the recent
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gKWNjFagR9k&quot;&gt;CUFP talk by Julien Verlaguet&lt;/a&gt; - skip to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_detailpage&amp;amp;v=gKWNjFagR9k#t=1149&quot;&gt;19:00&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned a lot from running this session so we've captured the good, the
bad and the ugly below.  This is useful for anyone who'd like to run an
OCaml tutorial in the future and also for us to be aware of the next
time we do this.  I've incorporated the feedback from the attendees as well
as our own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fpdays2013/fpdays2013-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Heads down and hands on&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Things we learnt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Good&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most people really did follow the install instructions beforehand. This
made things so much easier on the day as we didn't have to worry about
compile times and people getting bored.  A few people had even got in touch
with me the night before to sort out installation problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many folks from OCaml Labs also came over to help people, which meant
no-one was waiting longer than around 10 seconds before getting help.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had a good plan of the things we wanted to cover but we were happy to
be flexible and made it clear the aim was to get right into it.  Several
folks told us that they really appreciated this loose (as opposed to rigid)
structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We didn't spend any time lecturing the room but instead got people right
into the code.  Having enough of a skeleton to get something interesting
working was a big plus in this regard. People did progress from the early
examples to the later ones fairly well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had a VM with the correct set up that we could log people into if they
were having trouble locally.  Two people made use of this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, It was great to have early proofs of the book and these were
well-received.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fpdays2013/fpdays2013-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;RWO books galore!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Bad&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our excitement to get right into the exercises, we didn't really give
an overview of OCaml and its benefits.  A few minutes at the beginning would
be enough and it's important so that people can leave with a few sound-bites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not everyone received my email about installation, and certainly not the
late arrivals.  This meant some pain getting things downloaded and running
especially due to the wifi (see 'Ugly' below).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few of the people who &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; installed, didn't complete the instructions
fully but didn't realise this until the morning of the session.  There was a good
suggestion about having some kind of test to run that would check
everything, so you'd know if there was something missing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We really should have had a cut-off where we told people to use VMs
instead of fixing installation issues and 10-15 minutes would have been
enough.  This would have been especially useful for the late-comers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We didn't really keep a record of the problems folks were having so we
can't now go back and fix underlying issues.  To be fair, this would have
been a little awkward to do ad-hoc but in hindsight, it's a good thing to
plan for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;The Ugly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only ugly part was the wifi.  It turned out that the room itself was a
bit of a dead-spot and that wasn't helped by 30ish devices trying to connect
to one access point!  Having everyone grab packages at the same time in the
morning probably didn't help.  It was especially tricky as all our
mitigation plans seemed to revolve around at least having local connectivity.
In any case, this problem only lasted for the morning session and was a
little better by the afternoon.  I'd definitely recommend a backup plan in
the case of complete wifi failure next time!  One such plan that Leo got
started on was to put the repository and other information onto a flash
drive that could be shared with people.  We didn't need this in the end but
it'll be useful to have something like this prepared for next time.  If
anyone fancies donating a bunch of flash drives, I'll happily receive them!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Overall, it was a great session and everyone left happy, having completed
most of the tutorial (and with a book!).  A few even continued at home
afterwards and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/richardclegg/status/393458073052139520&quot;&gt;got in touch&lt;/a&gt; to let us know that they got
everything working.
It was a great session and thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarkDalgarno&quot;&gt;Mark&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JacquiDDavidson&quot;&gt;Jacqui&lt;/a&gt; and the rest of
the FPDays crew for a great conference!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fpdays2013/fpdays2013-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;RWO Book giveaway&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Thanks to Jeremy, Leo, David and Philippe for contributions to this post)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>FP Days OCaml Session</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/fpdays-ocaml-session"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-10-22T22:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/fpdays-ocaml-session</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yallop&quot;&gt;Jeremy&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lpw25.net&quot;&gt;Leo&lt;/a&gt;, I'll be running an OCaml Hands-on Session at
the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fpdays.net/2013/&quot;&gt;FPDays conference&lt;/a&gt;. Below are some prep
instructions for attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Preparation for the session&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're starting from scratch, installation can take some time so it's
best to get as much done in advance as possible.  You'll need OPAM (the
package manager), OCaml 4.01 (available through OPAM) and a few libraries
before Thursday.  If you have any issues, please contact Amir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OPAM&lt;/strong&gt;: Follow the instructions for your platform at &lt;a href=&quot;http://opam.ocaml.org/doc/Quick_Install.html&quot;&gt;http://opam.ocaml.org/doc/Quick_Install.html&lt;/a&gt;.
OPAM requires OCaml so hopefully the relevant dependencies will kick in and
you'll get OCaml too (most likely version 3.12).  You can get a cup of
coffee while you wait. After installation, run &lt;code&gt;opam init&lt;/code&gt; to initialise OPAM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OCaml 4.01&lt;/strong&gt;: We actually need the latest version of OCaml but OPAM
makes this easy.  Just run the following (and get more coffee):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;opam update
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;opam switch 4.01.0
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;eval&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;opam config env&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libraries&lt;/strong&gt;: For the workshop you will need to check that you have the
following installed: &lt;code&gt;libffi&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pcre&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;pkg-config&lt;/code&gt;.  This will depend on
your platform so on a Mac with homebrew I would do
&lt;code&gt;brew install libffi pcre pkg-config&lt;/code&gt; or on Debian or Ubuntu
&lt;code&gt;apt-get install libffi-dev&lt;/code&gt;.  After this, two OCaml packages it's worth
installing in advance are &lt;code&gt;core&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;js_of_ocaml&lt;/code&gt; so simply run:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;opam install core js_of_ocaml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OPAM will take care of the dependencies and the rest we can get on the day!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Feedback requested on the OCaml.org redesign</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/ocamlorg-request-for-feedback"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-09-24T15:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/ocamlorg-request-for-feedback</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There is a work-in-progress site at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml-redesign.github.io&quot;&gt;ocaml-redesign.github.io&lt;/a&gt;, where we've
been developing both the tools and design for the new ocaml.org pages.  This
allows us to test our tools and fix issues before we consider merging
changes upstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a more detailed post coming about all the design work to date and
the workflow we're using, but in the meantime, feedback on the following
areas would be most welcome.  Please leave feedback in the form of issues on
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocamllabs/sandbox-ocaml.org/issues&quot;&gt;ocaml.org sandbox repo&lt;/a&gt;.  You can also raise points on the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/infrastructure&quot;&gt;infrastructure mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OCaml Logo&lt;/strong&gt; - There was some feedback on the last iteration of the
logo, especially regarding the font, so there are now several options to
consider.  Please look at the images on the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/wiki/Draft-OCaml-Logos&quot;&gt;ocaml.org GitHub wiki&lt;/a&gt; and then leave your feedback on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocamllabs/sandbox-ocaml.org/issues/16&quot;&gt;issue #16 on the sandbox repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site design&lt;/strong&gt; - Please do give feedback on the design and any glitches
you notice. Text on each of the new landing pages is still an initial draft
so comments and improvements there are also welcome (specifically: Home
Page, Learn, Documentation, Platform, Community). There are already a few
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocamllabs/sandbox-ocaml.org/issues&quot;&gt;known issues&lt;/a&gt;, so do
add your comments to those threads first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Wireframe demos for OCaml.org</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/wireframe-demos-for-ocamlorg"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2013-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/wireframe-demos-for-ocamlorg</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Making mockups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months, I've been working on various aspects of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml.org&lt;/a&gt; design project.  This covers things like the design, information architecture and how to incorporate new functionality.  One of the methods for thinking through these was to put together a bunch of wireframes using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.balsamiq.com&quot;&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/a&gt; and use these to express (and generate) ideas as well as get feedback quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven't used wireframes before, think of them as a slightly more advanced form of sketching things out on a whiteboard.  The best aspect is that it's far quicker, easier and &lt;em&gt;cheaper&lt;/em&gt; to iterate using wireframes than on an actual website.  As you'll see below, you can also convey a lot of information about how a site might work by showing people a clickable demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make this work public and I thought the best way would be to show you some screencasts of how the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;http://ocaml.org&quot;&gt;OCaml.org&lt;/a&gt; website might work and also make the demo available to all of you.  The three videos below cover three aspects of the site and I'd encourage you to go through them in order (about 16 minutes in total).  Apologies if my screen isn't particularly clear in the videos but you can visit the demo for yourself and see things in more detail (link and info on feedback at the end of this post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Video walkthroughs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who'd like to watch the videos back-to-back and scaled to fit your browser window, you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/couchmode/album/2301640&quot;&gt;view the Vimeo album in 'couchmode'&lt;/a&gt;. Otherwise, individual videos are embedded below (total time 16m17s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flex-video widescreen vimeo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768157?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=de9e6a&quot; width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;303&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Video Part 1 - Overview - http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768157&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;




&lt;div class=&quot;flex-video widescreen vimeo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768235?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=de9e6a&quot; width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;304&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Video Part 2 - Documentation - http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768235&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;




&lt;div class=&quot;flex-video widescreen vimeo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768273?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=de9e6a&quot; width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;304&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; allowFullScreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Video Part 3 - Continuous Integration - http://player.vimeo.com/video/61768273&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Public wireframe demo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A demo you can interact with can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ocaml.mybalsamiq.com/projects/public-demo/naked/0_home?key=b897ea86d8a8199c6e46b3295ddf630dfa33e5e1&quot;&gt;OCaml.org wireframe demo&lt;/a&gt; and image files for each page are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml.org/wiki/Wireframes&quot;&gt;github ocaml.org wiki&lt;/a&gt;.  Please bear in mind the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not everything that looks like it might be clickable actually is (and vice versa). There'll be a toggle on the bottom right of the browser window that will highlight what can be clicked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are parts of the site which are 'work in progress' and are marked as such.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The designs you see aren't necessarily final. Your feedback will help shape our decisions and the best way to provide it is via the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.ocaml.org/listinfo/infrastructure&quot;&gt;infrastructure mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>OCaml - Installation and hello world</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/ocaml-installation-and-hello-world"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2012-10-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/ocaml-installation-and-hello-world</id>
  <content type="html">

&lt;p class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;This post is part of a series where I'm trying to teach myself OCaml.&lt;br /&gt;
You might want to &lt;a href=&quot;http://amirchaudhry.com/thirty-days-of-ocaml/&quot;&gt;start at the beginning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's been a few days into my OCaml experience so this is a write-up of what I've come across so far.  I've spent more time reading background rather than getting stuck in so I've copied in some of the links that I've found interesting/useful at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are number of ways you can get OCaml on your machine.  The most obvious  would be to get the source via the &lt;a href=&quot;http://caml.inria.fr/ocaml/release.en.html&quot;&gt;release page&lt;/a&gt;, but you could also use something called &lt;a href=&quot;http://godi.camlcity.org/godi/index.html&quot;&gt;GODI&lt;/a&gt;, which apparently bundles a bunch of other stuff alongside the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't really want to install from source 'by hand' and I definitely don't need all the stuff that comes with GODI.  I happen to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; on my machine, so I checked to see if I can install that way.  Turns out I can, so that's what I ended up doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew install objective-caml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The current version of OCaml is 4.00.0 and you can check the version you have installed by typing &lt;code&gt;ocaml -version&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be aware that Homebrew has it's own installation process and depends on Ruby.  To get Ruby, someone recommended that I install via &lt;a href=&quot;https://rvm.io/&quot;&gt;Ruby Version Manager&lt;/a&gt;.  To be able to do the above, you'll need to have the OSX developer tools installed, which means having &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/&quot;&gt;Xcode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hello World!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is get a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hello_world_program&quot;&gt;hello world&lt;/a&gt; programme working.  Since OCaml is a compiled language, that means writing the necessary source code into a file, compiling it and then executing it.  In this case I only need one line that prints 'hello world' to the screen and I'm taking it from INRIA's site (&lt;a href=&quot;http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/u3-ocaml/ocaml-steps.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ocaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;ocaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, world!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take the one line above and save it in a file called &lt;code&gt;hello.ml&lt;/code&gt;.  Now we need to compile that file using the OCaml compiler.  At the command prompt, type the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;ocamlc -o hello hello.ml
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;./hello&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since I don't really understand the first line I should break it down. &lt;code&gt;ocamlc&lt;/code&gt; is the command to invoke the compiler, the option &lt;code&gt;-o hello&lt;/code&gt; means you want to name the output executable to be (in this case) 'hello' and the final argument is the source code file.  It's useful to look at the man page for &lt;code&gt;ocamlc&lt;/code&gt; to see what other options are available.  The second line executes the programme, which prints hello world to the screen with a line-break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also notice that I now have two other files in addition to the source, &lt;code&gt;hello.cmi&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;hello.cmo&lt;/code&gt;.  According to the man page, these are the 'compiled interface' and 'compiled object code file' respectively.  I have no idea what that means but removing the files doesn't affect the executable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;OCaml 'toplevel'&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though OCaml is a compiled language, there's something called 'toplevel' that allows interactive use (more on &lt;a href=&quot;http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml-4.00/manual023.html&quot;&gt;toplevel&lt;/a&gt;).  To enter this mode, you simply have to type &lt;code&gt;ocaml&lt;/code&gt; at the prompt so let's try running the above hello world program using toplevel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;$ ocaml
        OCaml version 4.00.0

# print_string &amp;quot;Hello, world!\n&amp;quot;;;
Hello, world!
- : unit = ()
# #quit;;
$&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; prompt is the command line and the &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; prompt is where toplevel is awaiting a new line of input.  The input can span multiple lines and is terminated by &lt;code&gt;;;&lt;/code&gt; (as in the source code).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To exit toplevel, type &lt;code&gt;#quit;;&lt;/code&gt;.  It took me three attempts to get that right.  I haven't really played around with toplevel much and I think I'm likely to stick with source code and compiling until I'm a little more comfortable with the syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's pretty much where I am for the moment and everything so far has been straightforward.  Obviously, I should push myself a bit harder :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the material I found and have been looking over for the last couple of days.  Useful as background but I'd say I'm in danger of (semi-productive) procrastination if I'm not careful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml-4.00&quot;&gt;OCaml Manual&lt;/a&gt; (from INRIA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caml.inria.fr/about/taste.en.html&quot;&gt;OCaml examples&lt;/a&gt; (also INRIA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Objective_Caml/Introduction&quot;&gt;OCaml Intro&lt;/a&gt; (wikibooks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ocaml.janestreet.com/?q=node/82&quot;&gt;Minsky on ML&lt;/a&gt; (Jane Street)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/steveyegge2/ocaml&quot;&gt;OCaml pros&lt;/a&gt; (Steve Yegge)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.podval.org/~sds/ocaml-sucks.html&quot;&gt;OCaml cons&lt;/a&gt; (Sam Steingold)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thinkocaml.com&quot;&gt;Think OCaml&lt;/a&gt; (PDF book)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;!--
    http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=112129
    http://dave.fayr.am/posts/2011-08-19-lets-go-shopping.html
--&gt;

</content>
</entry>

  
    <entry>
  <title>Thirty Days of OCaml</title>
  <link href="http://amirchaudhry.com/thirty-days-of-ocaml"/>
  <author>Amir Chaudhry</author>
  <updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://amirchaudhry.com/thirty-days-of-ocaml</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/jeremyandchanel/6131620285/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ocaml-30days/camel-bactrian-silhouette.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bactrian Camel Silhouette&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've set myself a challenge that over the next thirty days, I'll teach myself some &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming&quot;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OCaml&quot;&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt;.  This will be my first experience of FP in addition to learning a new language so I expect it'll be quite challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I go along, I'll try and write regular posts -- hopefully one a day -- describing my experiences and frustrations as well as the questions that occur to me.  I suspect a number of the posts might be summaries to help me organise my understanding, especially where things seem unexpected.  For the times where I can formulate well-posed questions, I'll put them up in places like &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/ocaml&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; as well as describing them here.  Either way, keeping some form of diary will be useful for me and maybe also for other folks who've considered trying out FP and OCaml in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I'm not completely new to programming but I would say I have any deep experience (especially compared to the folks I tend to hang out with). Just to give you a better picture, my coding experience so far has involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some C/C++ with a little &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-oriented_programming&quot;&gt;OOP&lt;/a&gt; programming for a High Energy Physics simulation (during my undergrad - a long time ago so I've forgotten everything)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/products/matlab/&quot;&gt;Matlab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bash_(Unix_shell)&quot;&gt;Bash&lt;/a&gt; scripting for analysis of neuroimaging data (during my PhD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_Basic_for_Applications&quot;&gt;VBA&lt;/a&gt; within MS Excel for analysing behavioural data (also during my PhD -- I really wish someone had pointed me to Python back then)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://learnpythonthehardway.org&quot;&gt;Learn Python the Hard Way&lt;/a&gt; (I keep dipping in and out of this)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tried to dump most of my old scripts -- at least those I could find -- into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amirmc/PhD_stuff&quot;&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt;, but I still haven't collated the Matlab bits.  You can judge my coding skills for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the 30 days, I'm hoping to have the ability to pick up and read other people's OCaml code and write basic stuff for myself.  I don't actually have a particular project in mind but I'm not going to let that be an excuse for &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll post again tomorrow with the mundane parts of how to get things installed and running on a Mac*.  Onward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;*Admittedly, I already did this some time ago but I want this series of posts to start right from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;



</content>
</entry>

  
</feed>
